A Guide to the Taconic Foundation records FA407
Rockefeller Archive Center
- Organization Records, 1959-2012; 3; 7.2 Cubic Feet 14 document boxes, 2 card files, 1 oversized flat box; 51.4 Megabytes 325 digital files
  - Quo Vadimus
    The Quo Vadimus (Where are we going?) file contains memos for the board, mainly from John Simon and Jane Lee Eddy, on the topic of long-range planning and the future direction of the Taconic Foundation. The 1996 material concerns the proposal by J. P. Morgan to assume the administration and management of the Taconic Foundation.
    As board meeting materials are lacking for this time period, the Quo Vadimus materials fill some of the gap in the records.
    - 1994-1995 (Box 196, Folder 1916)
    - 1995-1996 (Box 196, Folder 1917)
  - Research by Staff and Trustees
    - Affirmative Action, 1999 (Box 196, Folder 1918)
      Memo on Taconic's Equality of Opportunity portfolio, prepared by Lisa Philp for the September 1999 board meeting. File includes related reference materials. The memo also considers Census 2000.
    - Affordable Housing, 1998 March (Box 196, Folder 1919)
      Program review by Monica Neal.
    - Economic Development, 1998 September (Box 196, Folder 1920)
    - Economic Development and the Environment, 1998 March (Box 196, Folder 1921)
      Program review by Vince Martinez and related materials.
    - Educational Initiatives, 1998 April (Box 196, Folder 1922)
      Program memorandum by Karen Erdos.
    - Equality of Opportunity, 1998 June (Box 196, Folder 1923)
      Program memorandum by Melvin Mister.
    - Housing Design, 2003-2004 (Box 196, Folder 1924)
      Monica Neal correspondence and reference file. Includes material on Bronx by Design.
    - Limited Equity Cooperatives, 1999, 2001 (Box 196, Folder 1925)
      Memos by Monica Neal, correspondence, and reference materials concerning affordable cooperative housing. File was also labeled "UHAB (Urban Homesteading Assistance Board) Writing Project." These reports are preliminary to the Taconic Foundation's decision to fund research and publication on the topic by Susan Saegert.
    - Localization Strategies, 1998 November (Box 196, Folder 1926)
      Review by Monica Neal.
    - Moving to Opportunity
      Memo on Moving to Opportunity programs prepared by Monica Neal, September 2002. File is mainly a compilation of research articles and notes.
      - 2002 (Box 197, Folder 1927)
      - 2003-2004 (Box 197, Folder 1928)
    - Opportunities in Community Development, 2004 February (Box 197, Folder 1929)
      "Opportunities in Community Development: A Brief Survey for Small Foundations," by Monica Neal.
    - Residential School Initiatives, 1998 July (Box 197, Folder 1930)
      Program memo by Karen Erdos and Megan Coles.
    - Talking Points, 1998 November (Box 197, Folder 1931)
      "Talking Points for New Funding Directions," by Lisa Philp.
    - Youth Development, 1998 March (Box 197, Folder 1932)
      Program memo by Karen Erdos.
  - Research Supported by Taconic
    - Limited Equity Housing Cooperatives
      In 2002 the Taconic Foundation engaged Susan Saegert as a consultant to conduct a survey of the literature on affordable housing cooperatives in the United States and Canada, develop a bibliography on the subject, and produce a paper for a general audience on the value and impact of affordable housing cooperatives. The file contains correspondence between Saegert and Monica Neal; various drafts of the paper, "Limited Equity Housing Cooperatives," by Susan Saegert and Lymari Benitez, June 2003; and the authors' "Literature Review: Success and Impact of Housing Cooperatives."
      - General
        - 2002 (Box 197, Folder 1933)
        - 2002-2003 May, 955 Kilobytes 5 digital files (Box 197, Folder 1934)
        - 2003 June-December, 595 Kilobytes 2 digital files (Box 197, Folder 1935)
        - 2003 (Box 197, Folder 1936)
          File contains paper by Susan Saegert and others on "Limited Equity Co-ops as Bulwarks against Gentrification," March 2003.
      - Paper, 2003 June (Box 198, Folder 1937)
        File contains "Limited Equity Housing Cooperatives: A Review of the Literature," produced for the Taconic Foundation by Susan Saegert and Lymari Benitez.
      - Paper (Distribution), 2003-2004; 89 Kilobytes 3 digital files (Box 198, Folder 1938)
    - New Markets Tax Credits
      Grant-funded research and paper on "New Markets Tax Credits: Issues and Opportunities," prepared for Pratt Institute Center for Community and Environmental Development, by P. Jefferson Armistead, March 21, 2005.
      - General
        - 2002-2004, 33 Kilobytes 1 digital file (Box 198, Folder 1939)
        - 2005-2006, 239 Kilobytes 6 digital files (Box 198, Folder 1940)
      - Paper, 2005; 437 Kilobytes 1 digital file (Box 198, Folder 1941)
        Paper file contains one copy of the paper.
    - Past Efforts and Future Prospects in Youth Employment, 1989 November (Box 198, Folder 1942)
      Report to the Taconic Foundation reviewing the foundation's experience with the Smokey House Project and possible future directions. Report prepared by Marc Freedman of Public/Private Ventures and others.
    - Summer Learning Gap, 1998 (Box 198, Folder 1943)
      Report commissioned for the Taconic Foundation on "The Summer Learning Gap," by Joelle Greene and Deborah Stipek, UCLA Urban Education Studies Center.
  - Rockefeller Archive Center, 2012; 726 Kilobytes 4 digital files
  - Section 8 Housing, 2005; 1.3 Megabytes 15 digital files
    File pertains to the National Low-Income Housing Coalition's National Housing Voucher Summit.
  - Smokey House Project
    See also Taconic Foundation Lands, Danby, Vermont, Masterplan.
    - General, 1995-2008 (Box 198, Folder 1944)
      File includes 1995 Yearbook, clippings, and brochures; as well as copies of the grant record cards and an overview of Taconic grants to Smokey House through 2005.
    - Smokey House property, 2002 June; 2014:FA407:054; 32 still images (Item 2014:FA407:054)
      File contains two duplicate sets of prints, which consist of regular and panoramic photos.
    - Grants
      - 1978-1980 (Box 198, Folder 1945)
      - 1981-1984 (Box 198, Folder 1946)
      - 1985-1987 (Box 199, Folder 1947)
      - 1988-1997, 2002-2005, 2010 (Box 199, Folder 1948)
      - 1988-1997, 2002-2005, 2010 (Box 199, Folder 1948 A)
    - Property Transfer, Tax Filings, and Pension Plan, 2002-2009 (Box 199, Folder 1949)
      File includes copies of memos relating to the transfer of the property to Smokey House. For tax material see also the file for Vermont Registration and Real Estate Taxes.The 1992 document concerns the proposed sale of forestland to the U.S. Forest Service.
  - Spend-Down Process: Grantee Presentations, 2011 (Box 199, Folder 1950)
    Presentation material by the Center for Community Change, Citizens' Committee for Children of New York, New York Lawyers for the Public Interest, the Opportunity Agenda, and the Pratt Center for Community Development, with reference to the proposed Taconic Fellowship program.
  - Spend-Down Process: Grant Letters, 2012-2013 (Box 199, Folder 1951)
    Contains announcement letters, grant agreements, and letters of acknowledgement or receipt.
  - Spend-Down Process: Grant Letters, 2012-2013 (Box 199, Folder 1951 A)
  - Spend-Down Process: Grant Proposals, 2011 January-February (Box 199, Folder 1952)
    Proposals by Center for Community Change,Center for Social Inclusion, and Citizens' Committee for Children of New York.
  - Spend-Down Process: Quo Vadimus
    - General, 2008-2009 (Box 199, Folder 1953)
      File contains memos, board correspondence, and reference materials concerning Taconic's funding history and final direction.
    - Board Memos and Correspondence, 2008-2011; 3.3 Megabytes 17 digital files (Box 199, Folder 1954)
      File includes correspondence and memos by John Simon and Melvin Mister.
    - Four Program Memos, 2008-2011; 2008; 2.3 Megabytes 23 digital files
      Memos address possible programs within four targeted areas: Affordable Housing and Community Development, Race Relations, Social Entrepreneurship, and Youth organizations.
    - Reference Materials, 2004-2010; 12.2 Megabytes 9 digital files (Box 199, Folder 1955)
      File contains articles, papers, and reports on race and justice and community and economic development. Publications include: Maggie Potapchuk, Cultivating Interdependence: A Guide for Race Relations and Racial Justice Organizations (published by the Joint Center for Political and Economic Studies), 2004; and Ruth Masterson, Closing Shop: When Small Foundations Get Out of the Foundation Business, 2009.
    - Survey, 2009; 395 Kilobytes 9 digital files
      The Taconic Foundation conducted a survey of grantee organizations concerning the effects of the economic downturn.
    - Write-Ups, 2009; 650 Kilobytes 15 digital files
      File contains summary statements on organizations nominated for spend-down grant funding in 2009. Statements include information on their programs, funding history, sources of support, and reasons for recommending them.
  - Spend-Down Process: 2012, 2012-2013; 6.7 Megabytes 35 digital files
    File contains some confidential material which is restricted variously for ten or twenty years from date of creation. Open in 2033.
  - Strategy Paper, 1998, 2004-2005
    The file concerns the Taconic Foundation's February 2004 paper "Opportunities in Community Development: A Brief Survey for Small Foundations," written by Monica Neal.
    - General, 2004-2005; 1.1 Megabytes 26 digital files
      Materials concern Taconic's funding history and guidelines and its narrowing focus on community and youth development. "Opportunities in Community Development" served as a kind of a roadmap for the Taconic Foundation's own program direction.
    - Megan Coles, 1998; 92 Kilobytes 4 digital files
      Memos concerning Summer Learning Gap, Youth Development, and Residential Schools.
  - Taconic Foundation for Social Justice, 2013 (Box 199, Folder 1956)
    Confidential material - Restricted for twenty years from date of creation. Open in 2034.
  - Taconic Foundation Lands, Danby, Vermont, Masterplan, 1992 October 26; 1 oversized box (Box 209)
    Draft, October 26, 1992. Report, prepared by Rosemary Grimshaw of Linea 5, Inc., surveyed Taconic Foundation properties in Danby, Vermont, and made recommendations for their use and future disposition. File contains three copies of the report: one includes a cover letter to Jane Lee Eddy; a second, with highlighting, is labeled SPC (Susan P. Curnan); the third is a photocopy with some marginal notations.
  - Taconic Foundation Reports
    - Report (1958-1964), 1965 December (Box 199, Folder 1957)
    - Twenty-Five-Year Report, 1958-1984 (Box 199, Folder 1958)
    - Twenty-Five-Year Report (1958/1959-1984) (Correspondence), 1984-1986 (Box 200, Folder 1959)
    - Twenty-Five-Year Report (1958/1959-1984) (Correspondence), 1985-1987 (Box 200, Folder 1960)
      Folder labeled "Fan Mail and Cover Letters."
    - Annual Report, 1970 (Box 200, Folder 1961)
      Contents consist of published report.
    - Annual Report, 1982 (Box 200, Folder 1962)
    - Biennial Report, 1985-1986 (Box 200, Folder 1963)
    - Biennial Report (Mailing List), 1985-1986 (Box 200, Folder 1964)
    - Five-Year Report, 1987-1991 (Box 200, Folder 1965)
    - Five-Year Report, 1992-1996 (Box 200, Folder 1966)
    - Three-Year Report, 1997-1999; 63.5 Kilobytes 1 digital file Imaged from a 3.5" floppy disk (Box 200, Folder 1967)
      File contains correspondence and a draft of the report. There is no published copy of the report in the file.
  - Transition to J.P. Morgan
    File concerns the Taconic Foundation's decision to transfer its administration to J.P. Morgan. Materials include J. P. Morgan presentations to the Taconic Foundation, May 23, 1996, and January 9, 1997, and e-mail correspondence among Hildy Simmons, Joe DeLosa, and others, concerning the Agency Agreement between J.P. Morgan and the Taconic Foundation.
    - General
      - 1996 January-May (Box 200, Folder 1968)
      - 1996 June-December (Box 200, Folder 1969)
      - 1997-1998 (Box 201, Folder 1970)
    - Board Meetings, 1997 (Box 201, Folder 1971)
      File includes materials for January and May 1997 board meetings, and September 23, 1997, Investment Management Review.
    - Personnel, 1997 (Box 201, Folder 1972)
  - Trustee Files
    The Taconic Foundation board was known variously as the Board of Directors or the Board of Trustees; the terms Trustee and Director are used interchangeably here.
    - Trustees (General)
      - Clippings, 1996, 1998 (Box 201, Folder 1973)
      - Correspondence, 1998-2005, 2010-2012; 139 Kilobytes 4 digital files (Box 201, Folder 1974)
        File contains correspondence with individual trustees and with the board concerning appointments, meeting scheduling and other routine business, and particular docket items.
        File includes some confidential material which is restricted for twenty years from date of creation. Open in 2033.
      - Nominations, 1998-2004; 91 Kilobytes 3 digital files (Box 201, Folder 1975)
        File contains correspondence and curricula vitae concerning various trustees.
      - Nominations (Higginbotham, Leon), 1993 (Box 201, Folder 1976)
    - Curnan, Susan P.
      A youth employment specialist, Curnan was a trustee from late 1987 until 1996 (she took a leave of absence starting in 1994). From 1978 to 1982, she was Director of the Smokey House Project, in Danby, VT. In 1983 she joined the Center for Human Resources at Brandeis University, which collaborated on projects with Smokey House.
      - 1978 (Box 201, Folder 1977)
      - 1979 (Box 201, Folder 1978)
      - 1980-1981 (Box 201, Folder 1979)
      - 1982 January-June (Box 201, Folder 1980)
      - 1982 July-December (Box 202, Folder 1981)
      - 1984, 1986-1988 (Box 202, Folder 1982)
      - 1989-1992 (Box 202, Folder 1983)
      - 1993 January-August (Box 202, Folder 1984)
      - 1993 September - 1994, 1996 (Box 202, Folder 1985)
    - Doyle, L. F. Boker, 1989-1990, 1993-1996 (Box 202, Folder 1986)
      Doyle was elected as a trustee in 1989.
    - Dworsky, Alan J., 1991-1995 (Box 202, Folder 1987)
    - Eddy, Jane Lee J.: Biography and C.V., 1988-1989 (Box 202, Folder 1988)
    - Eddy, Jane Lee J.: Council on Foundations Award, 1996-1997 (Box 202, Folder 1989)
      Jane Lee Eddy received the 1996 Distinguished Grantmaker Award from the Council on Foundations. The file contains her acceptance speech, an interview with her published in Foundation News and Commentary, and letters of congratulations.
    - Eddy, Jane Lee J.: Council on Foundations Award, 1996 (Box 202, Folder 1990)
      Article in Foundation News and Quarterly, March/April 1966.
    - Eddy, Jane Lee: Testimony (on Youth Employment)
      File contains various speeches and addresses concerning worksite training and youth employment programs. Jane Lee Eddy spoke to the Northeast/Midwest Congressional Coalition Conference on "Shaping the Workforce of the Future" in October 1983, and Representative Hamilton Fish, who chaired her panel, introduced her testimony into the Congressional Record for November 2, 1983.
      - 1981-1985 (Box 202, Folder 1991)
      - 1987-1989 (Box 202, Folder 1992)
    - Entenman, Edith: Obituary, 1979 (Box 203, Folder 1993)
    - Fleming, Harold C.: Correspondence
      Harold Fleming joined and directed the Southern Regional Council from around 1947 to the early 1960s. In 1961, at Stephen Currier's urging, he established the Potomac Institute, which he headed as executive director and later president and president emeritus until his death in 1992. He was also a trustee of the Taconic Foundation. Later materials concern his memorial and the posthumous publication of his manuscript history, The Potomac Chronicle.
      - 1959-1963 (Box 203, Folder 1994)
      - 1967-1969, 1975-1989 (Box 203, Folder 1995)
      - 1992-1996 (Box 203, Folder 1996)
    - Fleming, Harold C.: Manuscript
      Manuscript and draft of Fleming's "Potomac Chronicle." File includes correspondence concerning the book's publication.
      - (Draft), circa 1990 (Box 203, Folder 1997)
      - 1993-1996 (Box 203, Folder 1998)
    - Fleming, Harold C.: Speeches and Writings, 1961, 1965-1972 (Box 203, Folder 1999)
    - Fleming, Harold C.: Speeches and Writings, 1974-1991 (Box 203, Folder 2000)
    - Garrison, Lloyd K.
      Garrison died on October 2, 1991.
      The file also includes correspondence with Lloyd K. Garrison's son, Lloyd M. Garrison, from 1990 to 1996.
      - 1958-1969 (Box 204, Folder 2001)
      - 1970-1974 (Box 204, Folder 2002)
      - 1975-1979 (Box 204, Folder 2003)
      - 1980-1987 (Box 204, Folder 2004)
      - 1988-1996 (Box 204, Folder 2005)
    - Garrison, William Lloyd (Letters of), 1967 (Box 204, Folder 2006)
      Request by editor for a copy of a William Lloyd Garrison letter framed and hanging in the Taconic Foundation office.
    - Green, Bill: General, 1993-1995, 2002; 65 Kilobytes 3 digital files (Box 204, Folder 2007)
    - Green, Bill: Memorial Lecture Series
      - General, 2003-2010; 1 Megabytes 15 digital files (Box 204, Folder 2008)
        See also grant file for New School University (Milano Graduate School).
      - Advisory Committee Minutes, 2005; 50 Kilobytes 2 files
      - Speaker Biographies, 2009; 754 Kilobytes 6 digital files
    - Hirshon, Dorothy, 1971-1994 (Box 204, Folder 2009)
    - Jordan, Vernon E., Jr., 1972, 1980-1994 (Box 204, Folder 2010)
    - Simon, John G.
      - 1967-1983 (Box 205, Folder 2012)
      - 1984-1988 (Box 205, Folder 2013)
      - 1989-1990, 1996 (Box 205, Folder 2014)
    - Mister, Melvin A., 1986-1994, 2007; 35 Kilobytes 1 digital file (Box 204, Folder 2011)
    - White, Veronica, 2004-2010 (Box 205, Folder 2015)
  - Union Settlement Federal Credit Union
    The Union Settlement Federal Credit Union was a Program-Related Investment of the Taconic Foundation. The credit union served the East Harlem community and was also known as the East Harlem Community Development Credit Union.
    File contains financial reports, account statements, and certificates of acknowledgment for the Taconic Foundation's contributions as a non-member depositor.
    - 1970-1979 (Box 205, Folder 2016)
    - 1980-1995, 2000-2002 (Box 205, Folder 2017)
  - Vermont Registration and Real Estate Taxes, 1999-2004 (Box 205, Folder 2018)
- Tax Returns, 1958-1992; 4; 2.63 Cubic Feet 2 records cartons
  This series contains the Taconic Foundation's federal Form 990 filings for 1958–1992, and its New York State Annual Report of Charitable Organization forms for 1967–1984.
  - Federal Tax Returns, 1958 (Box 212)
  - Federal Tax Returns, 1959 (Box 212)
  - Federal Tax Returns, 1960 (Box 212)
  - Federal Tax Returns, 1961 (Box 212)
  - Federal Tax Returns, 1962 (Box 212)
  - Federal Tax Returns, 1963 (Box 212)
  - Federal Tax Returns, 1964 (Box 212)
  - Federal Tax Returns, 1965 (Box 212)
  - Federal Tax Returns, 1966 (Box 212)
  - Federal Tax Returns, 1967 (Box 212)
  - Federal Tax Returns, 1968 (Box 212)
  - Federal Tax Returns, 1969 (Box 212)
  - Federal Tax Returns, 1970 (Box 212)
  - Federal Tax Returns, 1971 (Box 212)
  - Federal Tax Returns, 1972 (Box 212)
  - Federal Tax Returns, 1973 (Box 212)
  - Federal Tax Returns, 1974 (Box 212)
  - Federal Tax Returns, 1975 (Box 212)
  - Federal Tax Returns, 1976 (Box 212)
  - Federal Tax Returns, 1977 (Box 212)
  - Federal Tax Returns, 1978 (Box 213)
  - Federal Tax Returns, 1979 (Box 213)
  - Federal Tax Returns, 1980 (Box 213)
  - Federal Tax Returns, 1981 (Box 213)
  - Federal Tax Returns, 1982 (Box 213)
  - Federal Tax Returns, 1983 (Box 213)
  - Federal Tax Returns, 1984 (Box 213)
  - Federal Tax Returns, 1985 (Box 213)
  - Federal Tax Returns, 1986 (Box 213)
  - Federal Tax Returns, 1987 (Box 213)
  - Federal Tax Returns, 1988 (Box 213)
  - Federal Tax Returns, 1989 (Box 213)
  - Federal Tax Returns, 1990 (Box 213)
  - Federal Tax Returns, 1991 (Box 213)
  - Federal Tax Returns, 1992 (Box 213)
  - New York State Returns, 1967 (Box 213)
  - New York State Returns, 1968 (Box 213)
  - New York State Returns, 1969 (Box 213)
  - New York State Returns, 1970 (Box 213)
  - New York State Returns, 1971 (Box 213)
  - New York State Returns, 1972 (Box 213)
  - New York State Returns, 1973 (Box 213)
  - New York State Returns, 1974 (Box 213)
  - New York State Returns, 1975 (Box 213)
  - New York State Returns, 1976 (Box 213)
  - New York State Returns, 1977 (Box 213)
  - New York State Returns, 1978 (Box 213)
  - New York State Returns, 1979 (Box 213)
  - New York State Returns, 1980 (Box 213)
  - New York State Returns, 1981 (Box 213)
  - New York State Returns, 1982 (Box 213)
  - New York State Returns, 1983 (Box 213)
  - New York State Returns, 1984 (Box 213)